There are countless humorous media creators
也可以搞笑自媒体千千万
but Dean Xiao Chao stands out
小潮院长独一份
If you analyze it from an academic perspective
你如果用学院派的方式去分析
Xiao Chao doesn't keep a diary
小潮一看一个不记事
The content is almost devoid of information.
他的内容呢信息密度接近于零
The jokes are often outdated.
笑点设计经常很旧
The production quality and editing also seem quite average.
拍摄质量和后期剪辑看上去也比较普通
The pacing is just okay.
节奏也就那样
But these things aren't crucial.
但是呢这些都不重要
Audiences watch Xiao Chao and Mai Gou for the same reason.
观众看小潮院长和看买购的原理是一样的
Music is just the excuse for everyone to gather.
音乐就是大家聚在一起的由头
It's fine even if our DER sings off-key.
我们家DER儿唱破音了也没关系
What truly matters is...
真正重要的是什么
It's the bond and shared experiences among band members
是乐队成员之间的羁绊和共同经历
It's this relational aspect that's truly crucial
他们之间的这种关系性才是关键
The benefits of this relational aspect are immense
这种关系性带来的收益是巨大的
The stickiness of Xiaoyuan's account is remarkably high
小学院讲账号的粘性堪称夸张
His average view count is approaching the number of his followers.
他的平均播放数接近了粉丝数量
I counted the 20 episodes of videos that Dean Xiao Chen borrowed.
我统计了一下小陈院长借20期的视频
Totaling 245 million views
总计2亿4500万播放
With an average of over 12 million views per episode
均播在1200万以上
In comparison to Film Storm, which has a similar scale
对比和他体量差不太多的影视飓风
Film Storm has only 21.3 million views on average over the last 20 episodes. This comparison is not to say that Film Storm has poor traffic. It's just that President Xiao Chao's numbers are unrealistically high. So, moving on, I also checked my own view counts, The total views for my last two videos are 9.8 million.
影视飓风近20期均播只有213万 这个对比绝不是说影视飓风流量差 都是小潮院长实在高的太夸张了 然后呢 顺便我还同连自己的播放量 我最近二期视频总的播放量是980万
The total views for 20 episodes don't match up to President Xiao Chao's single episode.
20期总播放量不如小潮院长一期
Additionally, regarding the relationship,
以及呢关系性
there's also the matter of revenue.
还有一个收益就是
Dean Xiao Chen's team
小陈院长团队
has an astonishing ability to incubate new channel matrices
孵化新号矩阵的能力是非常惊人的
every member of Captain Xiao's team has high IP stickiness
小船长团队每一个成员都是IP粘性也都高的
abstract
抽象
Most of them are creators with an average view count higher than their follower count.
基本上都是均播大于粉丝量的主
to be honest
说实话
major influencer teams aren't short of IP matrices
大网红团队搞IP矩阵不算少
but generally, they only incubate one or two subsidiary IPs
但一般来说呢都只孵化出一两个附属IP
and these sub-IPs can't independently form a strong presence
而且这些子P也都做不到单独形成战斗力
They need to collaborate with the main account of the master.
他们需要和主的主号去联动
Only then can they achieve significant traffic.
才能有大的流量
For example, the Film Storm team.
就比如说啊影视飓风团队
We know Qingqingzi,
虽然我们知道青青子
and we know Li Siwei.
知道李四维
But this is a manifestation of the main Film Storm account's influence spilling over.
但这是影视飓风主号影响力溢出的一种表现
It's quite different from the widespread presence of IP like Dean Xiaochao.
和小潮院长这种IP遍地开花不要钱一样的状态
There is a fundamental difference.
有本质区别
The Xiaochao team
小潮team
It's essentially the most impressive IP universe you can find within the Chinese internet.
基本上就是中文互联网网内
So, the benefits of these relational ties are an exaggerated level of stickiness and this IP universe.
你能看到的最厉害的IP宇宙
Alright.
那么好
But what's the cost?
关系性带来的收益是夸张的粘性和这种IP宇宙
The cost is that the audience has particularly high demands for the authenticity of the content from these small team leaders.
那么代价是什么呢
I wonder if anyone has noticed, most of these highly interactive comedy creators. To have more control over the content the show's effects are all purely acted
代价就是观众对小团院长 内容真实性有格外的苛求 不知道大家有没有意识到 大多数这种高互动性的搞笑博主 为了让内容可控性更高 其实节目效果都是纯演的
this can really offend people
这个非常得罪人
I won't give specific examples
我就不举具体的例子了
but it's really obvious
但是真的特别明显
many channels don't even bother to act
有很多号连演都不演
it's just pure script
就是纯剧本
audiences don't really mind
观众们也不太在意
as long as you have the show's effect
反正你有节目效果就可以了
I don't really care whether it's acted or not
演不演我无所谓
But if the elementary school principal does it, there will be an issue
但是小学院长这么干就会有问题
Because the audience would think
因为观众会觉得
Since you're in the video
既然你在视频里面
Your interactions can be staged
你们的互动是能演的
What about outside the video?
那在视频外呢
Could your relationship possibly be staged as well?
你们的关系有没有可能也是演的呢
That would become a significant problem
那么这个就变成很大的问题了
Enough to shake the audience's fundamental trust in them
足以动摇观众对他们的根本信任
So that's the price they pay. The second key point is conflict.
所以这就是他们的代价好第二关键词呢是冲突
Comedy requires conflict.
喜剧是需要冲突的
What is the most common conflict in Dean Xiao's videos?
小陈院长视频中最强常见的冲突是什么呢
The most common is the conflict arising from the unequal relationship between boss and employee.
是老板员工这层不对等关系带来的冲突
For example, Xiao Chao uses his boss status to bully employees.
比如说小潮利用老板身份欺压员工
But then gets turned around and pranked by the employees.
反被整员工倒
Turning the tables on Xiao Chao.
反天罡反压小潮
And ultimately gets punished after the game ends.
最终游戏结束后又被制裁
Many of his episodes, when it comes down to it,
他的很多很多期说穿了
That's pretty much it.
其实就是这么回事
The core is just that.
核心就是这样
Now, between the boss and the employees,
那么老板和员工
the conflict mechanism of cooperative competition among employees, is a key element of Xiao Chao comedy. It creates a very simple suspense. It's quite similar to Tom and Jerry, In Tom and Jerry, this adversarial relationship It provides suspense, tension, and a source of humor for the comedy.
员工和员工之间这种合作博弈的冲突机制 是小潮喜剧的核心要素 它形成了非常简单的悬疑 类似于猫和老鼠是很像的 猫和老鼠中 这种对抗关系 为喜剧提供了悬念和紧张感和笑调的来源
The underlying friendship between them,
而双方友谊的底色
however, can alleviate the discomfort caused by this conflict.
又可以消除这种对抗产生的不安
Just like how Tom always tries to catch Jerry and punish him,
就像汤姆总想抓住JERRY惩罚他
but doesn’t want to kill him.
但是不想弄死他
The audience understands that
观众也明白
Neptune and Xiao Yang won’t really be fired or fined,
海皇和小杨并不真的会被开除和扣钱
which aligns with the fundamental principle of comedy,
这就符合了喜剧的基本原理
allowing the audience to release aggression within a safe boundary.
就是让观众在一个安全范围内去释放攻击性
and making others look foolish
和让别人出丑
Xiaochao's account
小潮院长账号
the third keyword is expectation fulfillment
第三个关键词是预期满足
many online opinions suggest that Xiaochao has run out of new ideas
网上有很多论观点认为小潮没有新活了
but let's consider this
但是我们试想
if a team can achieve great results
如果一个团队能取得很好的结果
results widely recognized as excellent
市面上公认的好结果
and they also have well-known issues
而他们也有人尽皆知的问题
and these issues have persisted for a long time
而且呢这种问题还持续了很长一段时间
That's quite peculiar.
那么这个就很诡异
It's likely that the issue isn't central.
很有可能呢要么这个问题并不核心
or rather,
要么干脆
the problem itself
这个问题其实本身
is the solution to a more significant question.
构成了另一个更重要问题的解
In my view,
在我看来
Dean Chen doesn't lack for work,
小陈院长没活儿根本不缺
and this might just be their channel's unique way of operating. But why are the viewers tuning in for Xiao Chao? I think this principle is very similar to the show 'A Chinese Odyssey', 'The Big Bang Theory', '2 Broke Girls', and even 'How I Met Your Mother', as well as the value that Guo Degang and Yu Qian's crosstalk can bring to the audience.
甚至于这就是他们频道特有的运作方式 但这场观众为什么来看小潮 我觉得这个原理就非常像FRANCE武林外传 生活大爆炸 破产姐妹 包括老爸老妈浪漫史 乃至郭德纲于谦相声能给观众带来的价值一样
It's all about the relationships between the characters that the audience watches,
就是观众看的是成员之间相互的关系
which brings a sense of warmth,
能给自己带来这种温暖
and a feeling of closeness,
亲亲切的情绪价值
along with that unique sense of companionship.
还有那种独特的陪伴感
For instance, I have a friend in my life
比如说我生活中有一个朋友
who has watched 'A Love of Dashing Scholars' dozens of times
他看了十几遍的武林外传
and still watches it every day
到现在依然每天都会看
watching an episode of 'A Love of Dashing Scholars' after work
下班之后看一会儿武林外传
helps him relax and feel at ease
能让他的整个人松弛和安定下来
Dean Xiao Qiao also has this ability
小乔院长也具有这种能力
no matter how fantastical the outside world gets
也就是无论外界的世界怎么魔幻
these few people remain carefree and lighthearted
他们几个人还是那样没分没心没肺
full of laughter and joy
欢声笑语
The relationship is still as strong.
关系还是那么好
Then that’s enough.
那么这就足够了
This is the very unique model of President Xiao Qiao.
这个就是小乔院长非常独特的模
It’s the immense emotional value derived from consistently meeting expectations.
这种不断的预期满足所带来的极大的情绪价值
That’s the real secret behind President Xiao Chao’s account.
才是小潮院长账号真正的秘密
Good summary.
好总结
One last point.
最后再说一点
President Xiao Chao is truly unique.
就是小潮院长真的非常特殊
You won’t find a second like this across the entire Chinese internet.
全中文互联网你也找不到第二家的那种
However, in my view
不过在我看来
their account does have two underlying concerns
他们账号确实有两个隐忧
What's the first one?
第一是什么呢
The first is the overly stable expectations of their audience
第一是观众太过稳定的预期
which might become a shackle for them making it hard for their content to evolve rapidly the burden is heavy although even if they don't evolve their loyal fans will still find satisfaction But after a content cycle has passed, their IP might become outdated,
可能会对他们形成枷锁 要么他内容难以快速迭代 包袱很重 虽然就算他们不迭代 老观众始终都能获得满足 但是大家想一个内容周期过去之后 他们的IP可能会老化
making it hard for new audiences to relate and resonate,
新观众难以代入和共鸣
and the entire IP portfolio will enter a decline phase.
整个IP矩阵就会进入到衰退期
This places very high demands on them,
这个就给他们提提出了很高的要求
requiring them to constantly strive for change in the struggle.
就需要他们始终在挣扎中求变
The second point is,
第二点呢
their model,
就是他们的模式
the management costs will be significantly higher than those of other self-media teams.
管理成本会比其他的自媒体团队高非常非常多
You want your employees to feel like brothers
你想当你的员工都是兄弟
and family members, right?
还有家人的时候
Firstly, the distribution of benefits has to be different, doesn't it?
首先利益分配就得不一样对吧
In short, you have to share more of the profits.
简单来说就得把更多的钱分出去
When they're all brothers,
其次你都是兄弟了
all family,
都是家人了
can you still be fair in rewarding and punishing?
你是不是还能做到赏罚分明
Can you still ensure efficient execution?
还能做到高效执行
Can you still be impartial?
还能做到公正呢
You and the employees are starting to become friends.
你和员工工都开始做朋友了
Can Ma Haoning still maintain his authority as the boss?
那么马浩宁还能不能维持一个老板的权威呢
Finally, if anyone has an issue,
最后就是如果有任何一个人出问题
and there's a conflict with this employee,
和这个员工之间有矛盾
Xiao Qiao will also face,
小乔TM也会面临
a much larger public opinion problem than other self-media teams.
比其他自媒体团队大的多的舆情问题
Other teams can simply fire the person,
其他的团队只要把这个人开除掉
and the team will continue to function as usual.
团队该怎么运作还是怎么运作
But for Xiao Qiao, that's not an option.
但对于小成人讲是不行的
This is a significant test of Mahaining's management skills and the mental fortitude of a few key team members So far despite various issues overall the Xiaochengxuzhang account has maintained its core value and the trust of its audience
这一点就极其考验马浩宁本人的管理水平 和团队几个核心成员的心性 目前来看 尽管有各种各样的问题 但是大体上 小程序长这个号 保持住了核心的价值和受众的信任
In my view, Mahaining is a very thoughtful
马浩宁在我看来是一个很有思考
and highly capable content creator and team leader
也很厉害的内容生产者和团队领导者
The wacky Nestlé
逗逼的雀巢
The first keyword is expectation violation
第一个关键词是预期违背
If Dean Xiao Chen represents expectation fulfillment
如果说小陈院长是预期满足
then Nestlé is the epitome of expectation violation
那么雀巢就是极致的预期违背
Almost every joke from Nestlé tries to break away from the audience's expectations
雀巢几乎每一个梗都在试图跳脱出观众的预期
Nestlé's expectation violation has a few additional characteristics
雀巢的预期违背还有几个额外的特点
The first is that the expectation itself is not very mainstream
第一个是他的那个预期本身就不太大众
The expectation is either a joke
这个预期本身要么是个梗
or it comes from otaku culture or other cultural products
要么来自于二次文文化或者其他的文化产品
Even the expectation he defies
甚至于他反的这个预期
is itself a joke that defies some expectation
自身就是一个反某种预期的梗
So at times it creates a double-reversal of expectations
所以某种时候就形成了一个反反预期的效果
This is a double-edged sword
这也是个双刃剑
Audiences who are too immersed in reality
就是太过现充的观众
If they miss his original expectation
如果抓不到他的那个本来预期
They won’t get the comedic effect of the reversed expectation
也就get不到他的反预期的喜剧效果
And they will find it confusing
就会觉得莫名其妙
But those who like it will feel a sense of kinship
但是喜欢的人就会有一种看到自己人
Finding the feeling of home
找到家的感觉
Finding the sense of belonging
找到组织的感觉
So the second feature is
那么第二个特点是呢
He uses almost every conceivable form to achieve this Rather than go against it It’s a kaleidoscope of technical innovations For instance, he clearly draws inspiration from manzai, right Using a character or a voice-over to serve as the tsukkomi Yes, it’s a very common approach
他几乎用到所有能想到的形式去实现这样的呃 与其违背 堪称技术层面的万造梗万花筒 比如说他很明显的借鉴了漫才对吧 某个角色或者是话外音啊来充当吐槽意义 是的非常常用的一个方式
We can see in his videos
我们能在他的视频中
As we just saw, scenes from a Japanese comedy duo performance and a talk show
像刚才这样看到漫才日和脱口秀场景
comedy, even short skits
喜剧甚至短剧
a variety of expressive styles
各种各样的表达方式
and creative ideas
还有创作思路
What's the third characteristic?
第三个特点是什么呢
It's the incredibly fast pace of Nestlé's content
是雀巢的节奏非常快
so fast it's almost shocking
快得吓人
This speed has two aspects
这种快又分成两个部分
On one hand, the density of jokes is high.
一方面呢是梗的密度高
I counted the number of videos Nestlé has released in the last 11 periods.
我统计了一下雀巢最近11期视频里面
His total video duration is 3,532 seconds.
他的总视频时长是3532秒
with a total of 235 jokes.
一共有235个梗
That's an average of one joke every 15 seconds.
平均15秒一个梗
This is a remarkably high frequency.
这是相当高的一个频次
On the other hand, the pace is fast.
另一方面的节奏快
The efficiency of the jokes is high.
是梗的效率高
From setting up expectations or laying the groundwork to the punchline.
从预期设立或者叫铺陈到punchline
Or this expectation is violated
或者是这个预期违背
Generally around five seconds
普遍在五秒左右
Within five seconds
五秒以内
Rarely exceeds eight seconds
几乎不会超过八秒
Nestlé also uses an extremely fast speaking rate and tone
再加上雀巢一直在用超快的语速和话感
A different editing approach
换的一种剪辑方式
So it uses a very fast pace
所以呢用很快的节奏
Creating a brainstorming effect
就形成了一种头脑风暴的效果
Almost putting the audience into a state of flow
几乎能让观众进入到心流中
Enjoy an overwhelming viewing experience
拥有应接不暇的观看体验
Audiences who fall for this will get an extra thrill
吃这一套的观众就会有超额的快感
What's the fourth feature?
第四个特点是什么
Nestlé often employs some sophisticated tactics For instance, running gags Or breaking the fourth wall Running gags For example, the genuine emotion displayed at the old funeral In this episode, the thought of Jingwei not being able to reach the keepsakes on the top shelf He just wanted to laugh Then he thought about Jingwei roasting in the fire
是雀巢经常使用一些高级的招 比如说连环梗 或者打破第四面墙 连环港 比如说在老版葬礼上的真情流露 这期一想到经纬够不到柜子上面的遗物 他就想笑 然后想到经纬在火里回考
He wanted to laugh again
他又想笑
Then he imagined Jingwei hitting the dog
然后想在经纬再再打狗
He felt like laughing once more
它又想笑
In just 20 seconds
短短20秒
These three jokes were linked together
这三个梗就连连在一起
Forming a chain of jokes
形成了连环梗
Breaking the fourth wall was also used quite frequently
那么打破第四面墙用的也挺多
I need to jump more
我得跳多了
What are you talking about?
在说什么啊
How can we vote if this doesn't change?
这不换我们怎么票啊
I won 5 million in the lottery
我彩票中了500万
What are you saying?
你在说什么呀
The girl you like confessed to me
你喜欢的女生跟我表白了
What's the point of this certificate?
这个证说这个干什么呀
Stop
停
Many people caught us
很多人把我们接住了
Who's there?
谁啊
Have the audience send danmu to catch him
让观众发弹幕接住他
This advanced approach will keep the audience coming back for more.
这种高级的玩法会让观观众不断的回味
What was mentioned above are the technical features of Nestlé.
那么上面所说的是雀巢在技术上的特点
And in the past couple of years, Nestlé has evolved even further.
而最近一两年雀巢又再进化了
It has started to play bigger games in strategic planning.
他开始更频繁地在谋篇布局方面玩更大的套路
Creating more comprehensive surprises.
玩更整体的反预期
Or simply put in a comedic way,
或者干脆用喜剧向的说法
He has started to double down more frequently.
叫他频繁地开始翻番儿
This is also evident in the data statistics.
这一点在数据统计中也能看到端倪
The first half of each video in Nestlé's nearly 11 episodes combined
雀巢近11期每个视频的前半段加起来
there are a total of 150 jokes.
一共有150一个梗
On average, every 11.7 seconds.
平均11.7秒
In the second half, there are a total of 94 jokes, on average every 18.8 seconds. The stark difference in these figures It's because many of Nestlé's videos are not properly presented in the second half. not just aiming for laughs. Instead, it’s about adding value and emotional depth This requires additional space to handle
一个后半段呢一共九是四个梗 平均18.8秒 一个前后数据的悬殊差距 就是因为雀巢现在很多视频的后半段不端 不光是要搞笑 而是要上价值上感情 这个就需要额外的篇幅去处理
As a result, the density of jokes decreases
这样梗的密度就下降了
For example, when trying to hit the audience's funny bone
比如在试图击中观众笑点
The revelation of the true culprit in this episode
这一期里面对真凶的揭露
In the second half
后半段啊
Including the lingering traces of kindness in the true culprit’s heart
包括对真凶内心残存的这种善意
Creates two consecutive plot twists
形成了连续两次的反转
He must touch the audience
他必须打动观众
The final shot by the police chief in this episode
这期警察局长最后的那一枪
along with all the preceding flashbacks
和之前所有啊铺陈的闪回
reveals to the audience
让观众发现
that every joke earlier was actually a setup
原来之前的每一个笑料其实都是铺垫
This major structural twist
这种大结构上的预期违背
combined with a series of earlier surprises
和前面一系列预期违背
and the connections within smaller structures
小结构上的勾连
creates a whirlwind viewing experience
带来了漩涡般的观看体验
with a lightning-fast pace at the beginning
前面用超快的节奏
Dense jokes, man
超密的梗来man
keep the audience from catching their breath
观众让你来不及细想
then switch the background music to suspenseful
后面BGM1换悬疑
triggering goosebumps
开启头皮发麻
this nested expectation subversion
这种大套小的预期违背
It also formed the Nestlé video.
也形成了雀巢视频
Compared to other funny videos, the competitive barrier
相对于其他搞笑视频的竞争壁垒
of course, does this come at a cost?
当然这一点有没有代价呢
it certainly does
也是有的
Quqiao is a creator whose comments tend to be quite polarized. People you like, you'll eagerly look forward to watching their every share. But many people would say, 'What is this nonsense?' They can’t understand it Or find it bizarre Or they might be put off by some of Quqiao’s lowbrow jokes I’ve always thought Quqiao’s content is the best generational gap reducer
鹊桥是一个评论还比较满两极分化的创作者 喜欢的人就会特别喜欢期期看期期分享 但是有很多人会说这是什么玩意 看不懂 或者觉得莫名其妙 或者反感雀巢一些下三路的梗 我一直觉得雀巢的内容是最好的代沟减脂器
Meaning if your internet savvy is a bit lacking
也就是你网感稍微弱一点
And you’re not familiar with some of the memes and online lingo
对一些梗和网络网络用语没有了解
Those not used to the ultra-fast pace find it hard to adapt to the videos on QuChao.
不习惯超快节奏的都很难适应鹊巢的视频
So, Nestlé is naturally a channel that is quite niche.
所以说雀巢其实天然是一个
Its audience is quite limited.
受众相当受限的频道
He has so many followers
他粉丝这么多
it's only because he's so strong.
只是因为他太强了
This won't change unless he alters his core creative approach.
这一点他不动核心的创作模式就不会有改变
The second keyword for Nestlé is shame.
第二个鹊桥的关键词是耻感
As we mentioned earlier,
我们刚才说了
the later Nestlé videos aren't entirely absurdly funny, right?
后期的雀巢其实不全是无厘头的搞笑对吧
He often has deep emotional expressions in some of his videos.
他有些视频中经常有比较深的情感表达
But Qu Qiao seems to have a sense of shame about this kind of emotional expression
但是鹊桥呢似乎对这种情感表达有一种耻感
I think the whole team shares this feeling
我觉得他们整个团队都有
He is reluctant to directly acknowledge it
他羞于直接承认
The emotional connection between himself and the team
自己和团队之间的这种情感链接
He is hesitant to directly open up to the audience about his inner thoughts
他羞于直接向观众袒露自己的内心
This is not an obstacle to comedy
这一点并不是喜剧的障碍
I think it’s actually a driving force for comedy to some extent
我认为反而一定程度上喜剧的动力
And even fundamentally, the driving force behind many artistic expressions
甚至本质上很多艺术化表达的原动力
It's because creators can't directly use everyday language
就是因为创作者没有办法直接用日常语言
to express their emotions and thoughts in a conventional way Additionally, we can see from some public figures that the proportion of people in marginal situations within the Nestlé team is relatively high I'm not making any malicious speculations here but I believe their sense of shame in expressing themselves
用惯常的方式直接表达出自己的情感和思绪 另外从一些公开的人物我们也可以看出来 雀巢团队中边缘处境的人占比是比比较高的 我不带任何恶意的猜测啊 我认为他们的这种表达耻感
might originate from their developmental stages
有可能是源自成长阶段
when they found it hard to fit into the mainstream culture
自己难以被主流文化
or at school
被学校
Being accepted by the family
被家庭接纳
is not encouraged to express their true feelings and thoughts
也不被鼓励表达自己真实情感和真实想法
which is why they have developed this roundabout way
所以他们才形成了这一套绕着圈子
of speaking the truth in a seemingly playful manner
用看似戏谑的方式说真心话的表达习惯
I want to emphasize this again
这一点我再次强调
is not a weakness of the Magpie Bridge
并不是鹊桥的弱点
On the contrary, I think this aligns perfectly with The Spirit of the Age and generational characteristics.
反而我觉得这非常符合时代精神和代际特点
Because the new generation, to some extent, shares these expressive traits
因为新一代人或多或少都有这样的表达特性
in the postmodern era
在后现代
The most basic expressions of human emotion and values
人们最朴素的情感表达和价值
have been deconstructed to the point of being unrecognizable
已经被解构得体无完肤了
Some people may no longer be able to
一部分人可能已经没有办法
communicate their care for another person in a normal and smooth way
正常顺畅地对另一个人表达关切
let alone affection and reliance
喜欢还有依赖
expressing such simple emotions
表达那种简单的情感
can leave both themselves and the other person at a loss
这会让自己和对方无所适从
However, our human genes haven't completely changed yet
但是呢我们人类的基因毕竟还没有完全改变
we are still social animals
我们依然是社会化的动物
We are actually almost the same as ancient humans.
我们其实和远古人类几乎一样
We still have a need for simple and beautiful connections between people.
依然对人和人之间朴素美好的链接是有需求的
So defensive expression becomes a safe choice.
所以防御性的表达就成了一种安全选择
This defensive expression manifests in several ways. For example, pulling away your own chair. Saying 'I was just kidding' after a serious statement. Or asking 'You don’t really believe that, do you?', to deconstruct the seriousness. Or using extremely exaggerated expressions.
这种防御性表达具体体现为几种 比如说自己撤了自己的凳子 在严肃表达之后说哎我闹着玩呢 说你不会真信了吧 把这种严肃性解构掉 又或者是用极其夸夸张的
an exaggerated way to amplify one's emotional expression
比较颠的方式去夸大自己的情感表现
thus making the expression more playful
从而让表达游戏化啊
in fact, Stephen Chow also uses this technique
其实周星驰也会用这招
or another approach is to use aggressive language to undermine the warmth
或者另一种是用攻击性的语言去消解温情
for example, you actually care a lot about your sick roommate
比如说你实际上很关心你生病的室友
but you might say to him
但是你非得跟他说
hey, dad is here to check on his son's health
哎爹来关心儿子健康了
this is a similar approach
这个就是类似的方式
these three methods are frequently mixed and used by Nestlé
这三种方式雀巢都会高频的进行混用
I think this is also a potential reason why Gen Z feels comfortable with Nestlé.
我觉得这也是零零后们
Even when it comes to serious emotional expressions,
看雀巢觉得舒服的一个潜在原因
it never makes anyone feel awkward.
就是哪怕他有严肃的情感表达
There’s no sense of preaching,
但是也不会让任何人尴尬
nor any emotional manipulation.
不会有那种说教感
Instead, it leaves a lingering taste that touches people’s hearts.
还有情感绑架
Like the episode where an employee who had been with me for 10 years left.
而是会让人砸吧砸吧味儿之后有所感动
It’s works like this that resonate with us.
就像那期陪伴了我10年的员工离开了
This sense of shame is also a significant characteristic of the Nestlé account.
这种耻感也是雀巢账号非常大的一个特点
The third keyword for Nestlé is continuous improvement.
第三个雀巢的关键词是无限进步啊
This is what I admire most about Nestlé.
这是我最佩服鹊桥的地方
They are very ambitious in their content.
他在内容上野心十足
They are incredibly courageous.
非常有勇气
Let's look at the Nestlé account arranged chronologically.
我们看雀巢的账号按时间线排列
You can clearly see an evolutionary curve. From the earliest comedic game commentary to the courtroom series. The Holmes series And then there was the Doraemon series, which later took off in popularity. This period is basically a collection of jokes. And then it transitioned into live-action series
能非常明显的看出一条进化曲线 从最早期的搞笑游戏解说到法庭系列 华生系列 再到后面爆火起飞的这个哆啦A梦系列 这个这个时期基本上就是段子合集嘛 然后再开启了真人实拍系列
Starting from simple live-action skits
从简单的真人段子集
Evolving all the way to the current very mature
再一直进化到现在这种非常成熟
Very complex plot-driven films
非常复杂的剧情片
Nestlé can be said to innovate every year
雀巢可以说每年都在整新活
This is incredibly challenging
这是非常非常非常不容易的
Because when you haven't achieved success
因为你在没有获得成功的时候
Persistence is the hardest part.
坚持是最难的
But after you achieve success,
但是你在获得成功之后
persistence turns into the courage to change inertia,
坚持变成了一种惯性改变的勇气
becoming the rarest commodity.
就成了最稀缺的东西
Out of 100 creators,
可能100个创作者
After Doraemon (2005) received seven million views
在哆啦A梦啊七七千万播放之后
at least 80 will stick to their proven formula,
至少有80个都会在原有的成功模式的基础上
making minor adjustments here and there,
修修补补进行微调
and then launch similar new series to replicate that success.
然后开一些新的类似的系列去复制这个成功
Rather than taking drastic risks like Nestlé
而不是会像雀巢一样
to overhaul the foundation
冒大刀阔斧冒的风险去改地基
and attempt something entirely different
去做完全不一样的尝尝试
80 people would likely not be able to do it
80个人应该都做不到
So, this reveals a few characteristics of Nestlé
所以这背后透露出雀巢的几个特质
What is the first one?
其一是什么呢
The first is that Nestlé and its team
其一是雀巢和他的团队
possess strong learning and integration capabilities
拥有强大的学习能力和整合能力
There have always been people questioning Nestlé's approach As for the imitation of Magpie Bridge I personally think if a content team can stitch together something to the level of Nestlé it’s not about being lazy and copying specific content but rather about mastering a certain format or a particular style and seamlessly integrate it into your own video
一直有人在质疑雀巢缝合 至于鹊桥模仿 但我个人觉得 如果一个内容团队能缝到雀巢这个程度 不是偷懒抄具体内容 而是能把某个形式 某个风格吃透 再有机地融合到自己视频里面
and creating something that is highly recognizable
并且形成自己的一个很有辨识度的
a unique style of their own
独属于自己的风格
So, what's the issue with this so-called imitation?
那么这种所谓的模仿又有什么问题呢
Or how much content can people approach with this attitude?
或者说又有多少内容人能用这种态度去对待
Regarding the content they produce?
自己所所产出的内容呢
Secondly, Nestlé has a strong belief in its content capabilities and differentiation.
其二就是雀巢对自己的内容能力和差异化
They must have a robust confidence.
一定是有强大的信心
They can trust that even when changing formats,
他能够相信自己在换不同形式之后
they can still come up with interesting ideas,
依然能够想出有趣的点子
and create engaging content.
做出有趣的内容
They also have confidence in the connection between themselves and their audience.
他也对自己和受众之间的链接是有自信的
What Qiao grasps is not a specific creative formula
其三鹊桥掌握的不是某种创作创作套路
but an understanding of the core and essence of comedy
而是对喜剧内核和内容本质的理解
This allows him to switch formats
这样他才能去切换形式
Moreover, he has a strong ambition and passion for creation
其次呢是他对创作有强大的野心和热情
Don't think this is just a common occurrence
不要觉得这是一件平常事
Creating content can be extremely tiring
创作是非常非常非常非常非常容易倦怠的
After creators make money
创作者在赚到钱之后
it's not common for them to remain focused on the content
还能一门心思怼内容的并不算多
You could say
可以说
Nestle is the most fitting for the cinematic style
雀巢是最符合影视剧风
a Bilibili creator with the slogan 'endless progress' I hope he can continue to maintain such abundant creative energy What's the first keyword for Lux? It's information intermediary They all say Lux is an UPloader from the Varied Zone.
slogan无限进步的B站创作者之一 希望他能一直保持这样充沛的创作活力 好拉克丝的第一个关键词是什么呢 是信息中介 都说拉克丝是什锦区的up主
Have you ever thought about why he can achieve this?
有没有想过为什么他能做到这一点
Let's take a look at Lux's topic selection
我们来看一看拉导的选题
and it will become clear
就能明白
90% of the topics can be categorized into three types.
拉倒选题90%可以归为三类
The first type is cross-domain experiences.
第一类是跨界体验
It involves
这里面有他呃
personally exploring a new field, a cross-domain experience.
自己去接触一个新领域的跨界体验
For example, auctions, right?
比如说拍卖对吧
There are also instances where he brings others into a new domain,
也有他拉着别人跨界的
like frequently organizing various gatherings,
比如说经常组各种各样的局
getting two people from completely different backgrounds to chat,
让两个八竿子打不着的人对聊
or having an esports commentator guess prices, and so on.
或者让电竞解说去猜价格等等等等
These all fall under the category of crossover.
这些都属于跨界
The second category is product reviews and recommendations
第二类呢是产品测评和推荐
I won't elaborate on this further.
这个就不再赘述了
Everyone understands this.
大家都明白
The third category is crowdfunding.
第三类呢是众筹呢
The content involves Lux soliciting certain opinions from the audience.
内容也就是拉克丝去征集观众的某些看法
Or certain works.
或者某些作品
The camera drift project from a while back was a form of crowdfunding.
就像前一阵儿这个相机漂流计划就是一种众筹
What do these three categories have in common?
这三类选题共性是什么呢
Laks actually plays the role of an intermediary.
是拉克丝在其中充当的其实是一个中介角色
He serves as a middleman for the audience to explore a larger world.
他是受众看更大世界的一个中间人
Let's not talk about cross-border and crowdfunding.
跨界和众筹就不说了
The intermediary aspect is quite prominent, right?
其中的中介属性是很很高的对吧
It's purely about broadening the audience's horizons.
纯纯是让受众见世面
To understand another side of a different world.
了解另一个世界的另一个侧面的这种内容
Even when it comes to reviews,
而就算是测评
Laks's reviews are quite different from traditional tech and digital channels. In its product review video, the segment showcasing product features can take up to seventy to eighty percent while the traditional review method spends relatively less time on explanations and opinions
其实拉克丝的测评也和传统的科技 数码频道不太一样 它的产品测评视频里面 产品功能的对比展示部分能占到七八十% 而传统测评的原理 讲解和观点部分相对会比较少
Lux, who willingly acts as an information intermediary
拉克丝这种甘愿充当信息中介的
What are the advantages of this?
好的地方是什么呢
Lux rarely makes mistakes
是拉克丝很少翻车
he is someone who, in private, is known for his sharp judgment
他私底下接触起来是一个判断
which is quite incisive
非常犀利
I personally think his judgment is very sharp.
我个人觉得啊判断非常犀利
His opinions and inclinations are very clear.
观点和倾向很鲜明
He is a person with a strong sense of independence.
他也很有主见的这么个人
So, it's not that he lacks ideas.
所以说他并不是没有想法
Or has no opinions.
没有观点
But rather, he actively suppresses them.
而是他主动压制
He gives up a lot of personal expression.
放弃了很多的个人表达
What does he gain from this?
他换取到了什么呢
He gains the audience's trust in him.
他换取到了观众对他
Lower professional standards and expectations
专业性的更低要求和更低预期
also grant greater freedom in topic selection
也换取到了更大的选题自由
in the current harsh environment of the Chinese internet
在中文互联网上目前这么苛刻的一个环境里面
it manages to span across numerous fields in content creation
它能够横跨这么多的领域做内容
due to its role as an information intermediary
这是因为它的信息中介属性
significantly expanding Lux's range of topics
极大地扩充了拉克丝的选题范围
So, what is the cost of this approach?
那么这么做的代价是什么呢
There are at least two costs
代价至少有两点
The first cost is that the functional aspect of the Lux channel is relatively weak
第一个代价是拉克丝频道的功能性是比较弱的
The sense of gain is somewhat vague
获得感比较模糊
This will to some extent limit his fan growth rate
这会一定程度上限制他的涨粉速度
Another cost is reduced personal expression
另一个代价是更少的个人表达
which can make the IP less distinctive
会让IP变得不鲜明
If it wasn't Lux
如果不是拉克丝
It's other UPloaders
是其他up主的话
they might fall into the trap of frequent hits but people wouldn't remember who the creator is but Lux is incredibly talented He solved the problem in various other ways. We'll talk about that later. Lux The second keyword is project management guru.
可能就会陷入爆款频频 但是记不住作者是谁的窘境 但是拉克丝很天才的 用各种各样其他的方式解决了这个问题 我们后面再说 拉克丝 第二个关键词是项目管理大师
Lux is a top-notch professional.
拉克丝是顶级的真人
He's one of the strongest project executors I've ever seen.
他是我见过最强的项目执行者之一
And Lux isn't the kind of project manager who comes from an academic background.
而且拉克还不是那种学院派的项目管理者
He doesn't turn processes into rigid SOPs.
他不会把流程完完全的sop化
He doesn't write detailed contingency plans for every possible scenario.
写一个事无巨细的弯道和应急预案
He doesn't do it that way.
他不这么干
Lux will be very pragmatic in project execution
拉克丝在项目执行将非常的实用主义
Even a bit unconventional.
甚至有点野路子
He excels at simplifying complex matters.
他擅长将复杂的事物简
He sets the framework.
他去定下框架
Figures out the core issues.
想清楚核心问题
Once he's confident.
有把握之后
He moves forward decisively.
他就果断推进
Relying on experience and intuition to make adjustments.
靠经验和直觉去鉴赏进行调整
It's incredibly flexible
非常的灵活
It's highly efficient
非常高高效
Additionally
另外呢
Lux is also a creator with a very well-rounded skill set
拉克丝也是一个能力非常综合的创作者
Don't think this is common
大家不要觉得这很平常
I'm here to tell you responsibly
我负责任的告诉大家
Most content creators
大多数的内容创作者
often have significant strengths in certain areas but not others
其实都是能力有严重偏科的
People usually find complementary partners through group conversations
大家往往是用团对话的方式去找互补的合伙人
to address one's own skill gaps
去弥补自己的能力短板
Lux can almost single-handedly
而拉克丝呢几乎能一己之力
handle very complex projects
搞定非常复杂的项目
Nailing the entire video process
搞定视频的全流程
which is really impressive
这就很厉害
In his video project
在他的视频视频项目里面
he not only needs to plan and write content
他不但需要内容策划文案
but also has the skills for editing and post-production
还有剪辑后期的能力
and he also needs to excel in interpersonal communication
也需要他在人际沟通
Multithreaded time management Outsourcing management Monitoring progress Adaptive decision-making Including resource allocation And even managing one's own emotions, all require strong skills To handle all those tasks I think the camera drift project is a great example
多线程的时间管理 外包管理 盯进度 应变决策 还有包括资源调动 甚至自己的情绪管理方面都具备比较强的能力 才能整他的那些活 我觉得相机漂流项目就是拉克丝呃
Of project management and advancement capabilities
项目管理和推进能力的一个极佳体现
It's a significant achievement
是一个集大成就
This doesn't seem as complicated as it might look
这个事儿看起来好像没有那么复杂
That means the camera travels around the world, right?
那就是相机全球跑一圈对吧
But in reality, it's incredibly challenging
但实际上非常非常不好搞
Just imagine
你想象一下
You need to contact the candidates
你需要联系联系候选人
You need to screen them
你需要去筛选
You need to keep track of the progress over a year
你需要在长达一年的时间里
constantly diverting your attention to monitor it
一直分神来盯这个进度
Conditions and policies vary from country to country.
每个国家的条件和政策是不一样的
He often has to handle emergencies as well.
还经常需要他来处理突发情况
For instance, logistics-related issues.
比如说物流相关的问题
And in the end, he managed to land the video smoothly.
而最终他能够把这个视频平稳落地
Creating a hit.
整出来一个爆款
Moreover, he can also organize
而且他还能进一步的办起来
a medium-sized offline exhibition.
一个中等规模的线下展
And it receives a positive response.
而且取得不错的反响
This demonstrates his exceptional overall capabilities.
这就是他综合能力非常强大的一种体现
I can only say that these talents bring such powerful project management and execution.
我只能说这些天赋那么强大的项目管理和执行
They also bring an implicit additional benefit.
还带来了一个隐性的附属收益
I mentioned the issues with the IPG points, right?
我刚才提到了i pg点上的问题对吧
Its topic selection covers such a wide range.
它的选题内容内容范围如此之广
Generally speaking, IPD memory points tend to decline.
一般来说其实IPD记忆点是会下降的
But Lux can make everyone remember her firmly.
但是呢拉克丝能让大家牢牢的记住自己
What does she rely on?
靠的是什么呢
On the surface, it's the sunglasses and that lazy, laid-back tone, right? This contribution is significant. It's his icon But I think the more fundamental reason is His exceptional project management skills Maintaining consistency across Lax's various video projects is excellent.
表面上看是墨镜和那股子慵懒的京腔儿对吧 这个贡献很大 就是他的icon 但是我认为更核心的原因是 它非常强的项目把控能能力 让拉克丝各个视频项目之间的一致性是非常好
He creates such a variety of different videos
他做这么多不一样的视频
You can randomly open Lux's third or fourth video.
你随便点开拉克丝三四期视频
Even if the topics seem scattered
哪怕选题是东一榔头
All over the place
西一棒子
Covering everything
什么都有
But you can see a very distinct
但是你可以看到非常鲜明的
The vibe in Lux's video
拉克丝视频的那股劲儿
in the way he speaks
就是他说话的方式
He believes in the editing style of the video.
他信视频的剪辑风格
and his distinctive aesthetic
还有他很有特点的审美追求
In my view
在我看来
The consistency in videos brought about by this robust project management capability
这种强大的项目管理能力所带来的视频一致性
is the true source of his IP's memorable points
才是他IP记忆点的真正来源
The third keyword for Lux is audience filtering
拉克丝第三个关键词是受众筛选
Lux's channel covers a wide range of topics
拉克丝频道选题广泛
and has a great aesthetic tone
而且审美调性比较好
which brings him a significant added value in terms of audience
这给他带来了受众方面非常大的附加收益
attracting a group of highly potential middle-class audience
能够吸引到一群包容性和探索欲都很强的
with strong inclusiveness and curiosity
高潜中产受众
which is very, very hard to achieve
是非常非常不容易的
It's difficult for Lux to pull this off
拉克丝能做到这一点很难
In fact, we could say it's almost a miracle that Lux has managed to do this
甚至我们说拉克丝能做到这一点堪称奇迹
This is the true wealth of Lux's account
这个是拉克丝账号真正的财富
and an important part of his commercial value
也是他商业价值很重要的组成部分
And the reason he can achieve this
而这一点之所以能够做到
is not some mysticism
并不是什么玄学
nor is it just luck
也不是什么运气
Think about it It makes perfect sense Lux himself is very open to new things, right? He approaches various things with an open attitude and it's clear that his consumption level is quite high So, those who are always critical of everything
大家想一想 这是非常make sense的 就是拉克丝本人他非常喜欢接触新事物对吧 他对各种各样的东西都抱以很开放的态度 而且他的消费一看也比较高 那么于是那些天天对什么东西都看不惯
extremely conservative and critical of high premiums
极端保守和批判高溢价的人群
It's unlikely that you would pay much attention to him
自然也就不太会关注他
Instead, he attracts people with good purchasing power
它吸引到的也自然就会是消费能力还不错
curiosity
探索欲望
and young adults
前年轻人
This
这一点呢
is a natural outcome of his content production methods and channel positioning
是他的内容制作方式和频道定位
which helps him filter out a high-potential audience
所带来的必然结果
Alright, three people per episode
帮他筛选出来的高潜的受众
three sentences each
好的每期三个人
You might have picked up on the point of my video
每人三句话
You might have figured out the point of my video by now.
大家可能也看出来我视频的这个意思了
I'm not trying to praise or criticize any UPloader
我并不是想要去夸或者骂哪个up主
Every successful self-media person isn't just lucky
而是希望去拆解他们账号背后的逻辑
I think by 2025, the video industry
每一个成功的自媒体人都不是白给的
Actually, I think the video industry will continue to thrive until 2025.
其实呢我觉得呃视频行业做到2025年
Accounts that might seem ordinary to you
已经进入到一个深水区了
are actually quite strategic in the industry
那么大家可能看上去平平无奇的号
Successful self-media people must have some talent
但是在业内看来都是有门道的
and personality traits
能做大的自媒体人一定是有一些天赋
that suit this industry
秉性
and they must have made some right moves
很适合这个扛行业
There were some key decisions
以及他们一定是做对了一些事的
that they got right
有一些关键的选择
These characteristics and decisions form their competitive edge
做对了
and the core identity of their accounts
这些特性和选择会构成他们的竞争优势
But they also come at a cost and can become constraints The self-media business is so complex with so many variables that there are indeed some objectively wrong choices but there's rarely a single best solution Everyone is figuring it out as they go
还有账号底色也是他们差异化的来源 但同时他们也构成了代价 会成为他们的桎梏 自媒体这个事呢因为太复杂变量太多 所以他有一些客观上错误的选择不假 但是往往并不存在唯一正确的最优解
after much deliberation
最终大家都是边走边试啊
So for this series
反复权衡之后的结果
if you want to see which accounts I'll analyze next
那么这个系列
feel free to leave me a comment
如果你们想看我后续再拆解哪些账号
and suggest the next account to be analyzed
欢迎给我留言
Then select the BILIBILI UP100 breakdown that follows.
然后选择之后的这个拆解的百大
Of course, there's also the possibility that it might not be part of the BILIBILI UP100.
当然也有可有可能不是百大
and my own interests to decide
那么我会综合大家的呼声
which accounts to analyze next
还有自己的兴趣去拆解
Finally, a quick shoutout using basic slow motion
选择之后拆解哪些账号好
Alright
最后非常快速的叠个甲用的基本减速
That's it for this episode
好了
I'm Lao Jiang
那本期内容就是这样
an UP main who likes to think deeply about things
我是老蒋
and share my thoughts
我是一个喜欢琢磨事
UPloaders who enjoy sharing their thoughts
喜欢分享自己思考的up主
and make sense
你要是觉得我说的东西对你有启发
please give me a follow
有道理
Welcome to follow me
欢迎你给我关注
And let's triple-combo if we're fated to meet.
而且三连咱们有缘
See you next time
下次见